Guide to the Phi Beta Kappa, Beta Chapter (Rice University) records, 1927-2008 UA 108
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Phi Beta Kappa, Beta Chapter (Rice University) records
1927-2008
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Phi Beta Kappa. Beta Chapter of Texas (Rice University)
UA 108
13 Linear Feet 24 boxes
The Beta Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa at Rice was established in 1929. This record group contains the history of the Beta Chapter from its inception up until 2008, as documented by correspondence, minutes, journals, financial records, and printed materials.
Biographical/ Historical note
The national Phi Beta Kappa Society, America's oldest and most prestigious honor society, was founded in 1776 at the College of William and Mary in Virginia. Membership in the national society is a significant achievement, which honors excellence in the arts and sciences. Election to Phi Beta Kappa is based on outstanding academic performance reflecting a love of learning for its own sake as opposed to narrow technical specialization or vocational preparation. To demonstrate the breadth of their intellectual curiosity, most students will have taken more than the required number of courses and studied in traditional academic fields outside their major.
The Beta Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa at Rice was founded in 1929. Since then, over 2,400 students have accepted membership. In addition, all resident Rice university faculty, students and staff who have been initiated by another chapter of Phi Beta Kappa are regarded as General Members of the Beta of Texas chapter.
Scope and Contents note
The Beta Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa at Rice was established in 1929. This record group contains the history of the Beta Chapter from its inception up until 2008, as documented by general correspondence, national correspondence, letters of acceptance, constitution and by-laws, minutes, register of members, journals, financial records, and printed materials. Included in the materials is correspondence and documents relating to the founding of the Beta Chapter at Rice University.
Conditions Governing Access note
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 1-5, 7-20, 22-24 stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Boxes 6 and 21 stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisiton note
Bulk of the records were donated by S. W. Higginbotham,1966 and 1976.
Related Archival Materials note
See also the guide to the Phi Beta Kappa Alumni of Greater Houston Records, 1969-2000, Woodson Research Center at http://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/university-archives/phi-beta-kappa-alumni.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges
Document Types
letters (correspondence); reports; constitutions; minutes (administrative records); directories
Subjects (Corporations)
Phi Beta Kappa. Beta Chapter of Texas (Rice University)
- Series I: Correspondence, 1927-2001; 97672
  - Subseries A: General correspondence (Boxes 1-3), 1927-2001; 97673
    - General correspondence, 1927-1928; 97674 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence, 1928-1929; 97675 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence, 1929-1930; 97676 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General correspondence, 1930-1938; 97677 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General correspondence, 1938-1942; 97678 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General correspondence, 1949-1955; 97679 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General correspondence, 1955-1957; 97680 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General correspondence, 1957-1959; 97681 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General correspondence, 1959-1961; 97682 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - General correspondence, 1961-1962; 97683 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - General correspondence, 1962-1963; 97684 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General correspondence, 1963-1965; 97685 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General correspondence, 1965-1966; 97686 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence, 1966-1967; 97687 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence, 1967-1968; 97688 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - General correspondence, 1968-1970; 97689 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - General correspondence, 1970-1971; 97690 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - General correspondence, 1971-1972; 97691 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - General correspondence, 1972-1973; 97692 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - General correspondence, 1973-1975; 97693 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - General correspondence, 1976-1981; 97694 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - General correspondence, 1982-1984; 97695 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - General correspondence, 1985-1991; 97696 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - General correspondence, 1992-1995; 97697 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence, 1996-1997; 97698 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence, 1998; 97699 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - General correspondence, 1999; 97700 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - General correspondence, 2000-2006, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: National correspondence, 1929-1999 (Boxes 3-5), 97701
    - National correspondence, 1929-1931; 97702 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - National correspondence, 1931-1932; 97703 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - National correspondence, 1932-1934; 97704 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - National correspondence, 1942-1956; 97705 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - National correspondence, 1962-1963; 97706 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - National correspondence, 1963-1964; 97707 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - National correspondence, 1964-1966; 97708 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - National correspondence, 1966-1967; 97709 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - National correspondence, 1967-1971; 97710 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - National correspondence, 1971-1972; 97711 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - National correspondence, 1973-1975; 97712 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - National correspondence, 1977-1987; 97713 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - National correspondence, 1988-1990; 97714 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - National correspondence, 1991-1998; 97715 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - National correspondence, 1999; 97716 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series II: Organizational and member files, 1928-2008; 97717
  - Subseries A: (Boxes 5-8), 1928-1959; 97718
    Scope and Contents note
    The first five folders in this series include the correspondence and documents relating to the founding of the Phi Beta Kappa chapter at Rice University.
    - History, 1921-1928; 97719 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - History, 1928; 97720 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Constitutions and by-laws, 1929; 97721 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1921-1929; 97722 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1929; 97723 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Ritual book, 1928; 97724 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Initiation and Banquet, 1932-1959; 97725 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Handbook for New Members, 1947, 1950; 97726 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "Form of Initiation,", 1956; 97727 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Manual for chapter officers, 1958; 97728 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Member certificates, 1930, 1932, 1951; 97729 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Samuel Elliot Morrison address, 1935; 97730 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Lectures, 1959; 97731 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Meeting notices, 1927-1959; 97732 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Chapter minute book, 1928-1940; 97733 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Chapter minute book, 1940-1959; 97734 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Minutes, 1959; 97735 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Senate minutes, 1930-1959; 97736 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Member lists and rosters, 1929-1959; 97737 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Register, 1929-1966; 97738 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Guest book, 1948-1961; 97739 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Minute book, 1959-1981; 97740 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Register (copies), 1929-Present; 97741 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1928-1931; 97742 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1931-1933; 97743 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1933-1938; 97744 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1938-1942; 97745 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1942-1949; 97746 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1949-1951; 97747 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1951-1954; 97748 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1954-1957; 97749 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1957-1959; 97750 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Annual reports, 1949-1959; 97751 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Ledger, 1929-1961; 97752 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Bank books, 1929-1963; 97753 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Bank statements, 1945-1959; 97754 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Balance sheets, financial statements, 1947-1959; 97755 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - IRS forms and correspondence, 1951-1959; 97756 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - News clippings, 1930-1933, 1959; 97757 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: (Boxes 8-11), 1960-1979; 97758
    - Constitutions and by-laws, 1967-1972, undated; 97759 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Initiation ritual, 1966, undated; 97760 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Initiation and annual dinner, 1967-1968, 1970-1972, 1974, 1977-1978; 97761 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Selection criteria, 1970-1974; 97762 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Manual for Chapter Officers, 1977; 97763 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Meeting notices, 1962-1977; 97764 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Minutes, 1960-1979; 97765 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Senate minutes, 1960-1971; 97766 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Senate minutes, 1971-1977; 97767 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Committee reports, 1973; 97768 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Membership lists, 1961-1969, undated; 97769 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Membership lists, 1973-1978, undated; 97770 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Alumni mailing lists, 1974, undated; 97771 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Floyd Seward Lear address, (reel to reel; 3 3/4 ips) Denise Levertov poetry reading, (reel to reel; 3 3/4 ips), 1963, 1973; 97772 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Prize committee, 1965-1966; 97773 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Teaching prize, 1977; 97774 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Lectures, 1960; 97775 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Freshman address, 1978; 97776 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Visiting scholars, 1961-1971; 97777 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Visiting scholars, 1976-1979; 97778 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Associates, 1978-1979; 97779 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - 32nd Triennial Council, 1979; 97780 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Bicentennial Bulletin, 1976; 97781 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1960-1963; 97782 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1963-1964; 97783 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1964-1965; 97784 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1965-1966; 97785 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1966-1967; 97786 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1967-1968; 97787 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1968-1969; 97788 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1969-1970; 97789 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1970-1971; 97790 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1971-1972; 97791 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1972-1973; 97792 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1973-1974; 97793 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1974-1975; 97794 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1976-1977; 97795 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1977-1978; 97796 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1978-1979; 97797 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Annual reports, 1960-1969; 97798 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Annual reports, 1970-1979; 97799 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Bank statements, 1960; 97800 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Treasurer's file, 1960-1979; 97801 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Invoices and receipts, 1962-1978; 97802 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Financial statements, 1960-1972; 97803 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - IRS forms and correspondence, 1961-1977; 97804 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - News clippings, 1961-1965, 1977; 97805 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Subseries C: 1980-1999 (Boxes 11-16), 97806
    - Constitution and by-laws, 1982-1983; 97807 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Selection criteria, 1982-1997; 97808 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Members in course, 1980-1998; 97809 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Initiation, 1980-1982, 1988-1993, undated; 97810 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Initiation, 1994-1999; 97811 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Handbook for new members, 1999; 97812 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Commencement calendar and programs, 1990, 1992, 1993-1994; 97813 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Meeting minutes, 1980-1985, 1992-1998; 97814 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Chapter reports, 1985; 97815 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Instructions and manuals, 1983-1988; 97816 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Instructions, 1991-1993; 97817 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Vice-president's files, 1981-1983; 97818 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Vice-president's files, 1983-1988; 97819 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Secretary's files, 1989-1990; 97820 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Membership lists, 1981, 1987-88, 1990, 1993-94; 97821 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Membership statistics, 1994-1997; 97822 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - National Honor Society meeting, 1997; 97823 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Lectures and seminars, 1982-1984, 1994-1995; 97824 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Teaching Prize, 1981-1982, 1984-1999; 97825 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Visiting scholars, 1980-1981, 1988-1993; 97826 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Associates award, 1980-1981, 1984-1985, 1988; 97827 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - 34th Triennial Council, 1985; 97828 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1980; 97829 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1981; 97830 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1982; 97831 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1983; 97832 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1984; 97833 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1985; 97834 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1986; 97835 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1987; 97836 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1988; 97837 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Letters of acceptanc, 1989-1992; 97838 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1993-1995; 97839 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1996; 97840 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1997; 97841 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1998; 97842 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Letters of acceptance, 1999; 97843 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Annual reports, 1980-1991, 1993-1994, 1997-1999; 97844 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Key and certificate orders, 1986-1989; 97845 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Key and certificate orders, 1990-1991; 97846 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Key and certificate orders, 1992-1994; 97847 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Key and certificate orders, 1995; 97848 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Key and certificate orders, 1996; 97849 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Key and certificate orders, 1997; 97850 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Key and certificate orders, 1998; 97851 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Key order invoices and correspondence, 1988-1994; 97852 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Student fee receipts and order forms, 1991-1992; 97853 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Financial statements and correspondence, 1982-1983; 97854 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Bank statements, 1983-1991; 97855 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Treasurer's files, statements & corresp., 1980-82, n.d.; 97856 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Newsclippings, 1981-1999; 97857 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Press releases, 1982, 1988, 1990-96; 97858 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - NCNB records, 1984-1991; 97859 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Sky Magazine article, "Key to Success,", 1990; 97860 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Teaching Prize, 1998-99; 97861 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Initiation, 1999; 97862 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Manual for chapter officer, 1999; 97863 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - New member packet, 1999; 97864 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Candidate lists, 1999-2000; 97865 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Handbook for New Members, 1999-2000, 2004-09; 97866 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Acceptance letters, 2000; 97867 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Subseries D: 2000-current (Boxes 17-20), 97868
    - Endowment, 2000; 97869 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Key & certificate orders, 2000; 97870 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Membership criteria, c. 2000; 97871 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Membership rosters, 2000; 97872 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Newsclips, 2000; 97873 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Registration cards, 2000; 97874 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Secretary's notebook, 2000; 97875 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Meeting minutes, 2000-02; 97876 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Teaching prize, 2000, 2002, 2005-06; 97877 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Annual reports, 2000-04; 97878 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 2000-04; 97879 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Press releases, 2000-04; 97880 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Initiation, 2000-08; 97881 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Acceptance, 2001; 97882 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Membership roster, 2001; 97883 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Meeting minutes & supplemental materials, 2001; 97884 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Secretary's notebook [1/2], 2001; 97885 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Secretary's notebook [2/2], 2001; 97886 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Registration cards, 2001-03; 97887 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Acceptance forms, 2002; 97888 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Course criteria, 2002-2003; 97889 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Secretary's notebook, [1/2], 2002; 97890 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Secretary's notebook [2/2], 2002; 97891 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Visiting scholars program, 2002, 2004-05; 97892 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Acceptance forms, 2003; 97893 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Informational brochure, 2003; 97894 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Membership rosters, 2003; 97895 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Secretary's notebook, 2003; 97896 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Triennial Council, 2003; 97897 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Meeting minutes, 2003-04; 97898 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Candidates, 2004; 97899 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Financial, 2004-05; 97900 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Membership Roster, 2005-2006 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Acceptance forms, 2006; 97901 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Press releases, 2006-07; 97902 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Visiting scholars program, 2006-07; 97903 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Acceptance forms, 2007; 97904 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Annual reports, 2007-; 97905 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2007-; 97906 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Meeting minutes, 2007-; 97907 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Membership rosters, 2007; 97908; Membership rosters, 2007 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Visiting scholars program, 2007-08; 97909 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Acceptance forms, 2008; 97910 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Membership criteria, 2008; 97911 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Selection process worksheets, 2008; 97912 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Key Reporter, 97913 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - "Insignia of Phi Beta Kappa", 97914 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Certificates, 97915 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - History compilations, 97917 (Box 20, Folder 12)
- Series III: Publications, 98170
  - "The Key Collection" catalog, 98171 (Box 20, Folder -)
  - 38th Triennial Council Meeting, 1997, 98172 (Box 20, Folder -)
  - 40th Triennial Council, 2003, 98173 (Box 20, Folder -)
  - 41st Triennial Council, 2006, 98174 (Box 20, Folder -)
- Series IV: Addenda
  - Finances and Correspondence, 1998-2004 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Finances and Member List, 2005-2006 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Sub-Series A. Index Cards
    - Houston Phi Beta Kappa Non-Rice Addresses, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Rice Phi Beta Kappa Current Addresses, 1970s (Box 23)
    - Rice Phi Beta Kappa-Master List and Associate Members, 1931-1972 (Box 24)